{"test_questions": [[{"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "We discussed about the problem so thoroughly", "optb": "on the eve of the examination", "optc": "that I found it very easy to work it out.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "We discussed the problem so thoroughly"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "An Indian ship", "optb": "laden with merchandise", "optc": "got drowned in the Pacific Ocean.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "sank in the Pacific Ocean"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I could not put up in a hotel", "optb": "because the boarding and lodging charges", "optc": "were exorbitant.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'I could not put up at a hotel'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The Indian radio", "optb": "which was previously controlled by the British rulers", "optc": "is free now from the narrow vested interests.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "is now free from the narrow vested interests."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I had known", "optb": "this yesterday", "optc": "I will have helped him.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I would have helped him"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A lot of travel delay is caused", "optb": "due to the inefficiency and lack of good management", "optc": "on behalf of the railways.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "on the part of the railways"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "One of the members", "optb": "expressed doubt if", "optc": "the Minister was an atheist.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "expressed doubt that"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I have got", "optb": "my  M.Sc. degree", "optc": "in 1988.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I got"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Having received your letter", "optb": "this morning, we are writing", "optc": "to thank you for the same.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If  you lend him a book", "optb": "he will lend it to some one else", "optc": "and never you will get it back.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "and you will never get it back"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "According to the Bible", "optb": "it is meek and humble", "optc": "who shall inherit the earth.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "it is the meek and the humble"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Do the roses in your garden smell", "optb": "more sweetly", "optc": "than those in ours?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "sweeter"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Block of Residential flats", "optb": "are coming up", "optc": "near our house.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Blocks of Residential flats"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You can get", "optb": "all the information that you want", "optc": "in this book.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "all the information you want"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The students were", "optb": "awaiting for", "optc": "the arrival of the chief guest.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "awaiting"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Sixty miles", "optb": "are", "optc": "a good distance.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Sixty miles is a good distance."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "They have been", "optb": "very close friends", "optc": "until they quarrelled.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'They had been'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When the dentist came in", "optb": "my tooth was stopped aching", "optc": "out of fear that I might lose my tooth.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "my tooth stopped aching"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is the duty of every citizen to do his utmost", "optb": "to defend the hardly-won", "optc": "freedom of the country.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "to defend the hard-won"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "No sooner did I open the door", "optb": "when the rain, heavy and stormy, rushed in", "optc": "making us shiver from head to foot", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "than the rain, heavy and stormy, rushed in"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If a man diligently seeks to come into the contact", "optb": "with the best that has been thought and said in this world", "optc": "he will become simple and unselfish.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If a man diligently seeks to come into contact"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You must", "optb": "remember me", "optc": "to post this letter.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "remind me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I shall certainly", "optb": "write you", "optc": "when I shall reach NewDelhi.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "when I reach New Delhi"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "On the busy Ring Road", "optb": "we witnessed  a collusion", "optc": "between a truck and an auto.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "we witnessed a collision"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Mr.Praful Patel", "optb": "is not attending his office", "optc": "for the last one month.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "has not been attending his office"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He couldn't  but help", "optb": "shedding tears at the plight of the villagers", "optc": "rendered homeless by a devastating cyclone.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He couldn't help"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He will certainly help you", "optb": "if you will ask him", "optc": "in a pleasant manner.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "if you ask him"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The brand propositon now therefore had to be that Keokarpin Antiseptic Cream is more effective", "optb": "because it penetrates deepdown (beinglight and non-sticky) and works from within", "optc": "(because of its ayurvedic ingredients) to keep skin blemish, free and helps cope with cuts nicks, burns and nappy rash.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The brand proposition now therefore is"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Will you please buy", "optb": "some jaggery for me", "optc": "if  you go to the market?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Most of the members at the meeting felt", "optb": "that the group appointed for investigating  the case", "optc": "were not competent to do the job efficiently.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "was not competent to do the job efficiently"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In these  days of inflation", "optb": "a ten rupee's note will not buy you", "optc": "even an ordinary meal.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "a ten rupee note will not buy you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He persisted", "optb": "to do it", "optc": "in spite of my advice", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "in doing it"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The long-awaited moment at last came,", "optb": "and we set out  for the station", "optc": "as merry a band of children as I have ever seen before or since.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "as merry a band of children as I have ever seen since or before"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Our conception of", "optb": "what should a science of mental life be", "optc": "has changed considerably since James' time.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "what a science of mental life should be"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is not coming tomorrow", "optb": "as he is having  a pain in the chest", "optc": "and has to see a doctor.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'and he has to see a doctor'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Many times the news has been published", "optb": "in the papers that the end of the world will be certain", "optc": "if a nuclear war breaks out.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The reason Ram", "optb": "is absent from his duty", "optc": "is because he is unwell.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The reason why Ram"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Azharuddin is one of the finest batsmen", "optb": "that India have produced", "optc": "over the decades.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "that India has produced"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The thief broke in the", "optb": "house at the", "optc": "dead of night", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The thief broke into the"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "May I", "optb": "know who you want", "optc": "to see please", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "know whom you want"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He said that he", "optb": "will mind if", "optc": "I refused his offer.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "would mind if"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Arun's parents died when he was young and", "optb": "he looked after his aunt", "optc": "who had no children.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he was looked after by his aunt"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Though child marriage", "optb": "has been banned.", "optc": "the custom still prevailed among some groups in India.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The custom still prevails among some groups in India"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My papa is", "optb": "in bad mood", "optc": "today", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "in a bad mood"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The warden", "optb": "forbade the student", "optc": "from leaving the hostel.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In spite of several reminders,", "optb": "he did not so far send", "optc": "any reply to me, letters.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he has not so far sent"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "As much as I admire him for his sterling qualities.", "optb": "I cannot excuse him for", "optc": "being unfair to his friends.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Much as I admire him for his sterling qualities."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Please try to understand", "optb": "that the dispute on this issue is between my brother and myself,", "optc": "and concerns nobody else.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "that the dispute on this issue is between my brother and me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "All  the furnitures have been", "optb": "sent to the new house", "optc": "located in a village.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All the furniture have been"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It does not matter how you do it;", "optb": "what I want is that", "optc": "you should finish the work within a month.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "I want that"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Though senior in age,", "optb": "his father is junior  than", "optc": "my father in service.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "his father is junior to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "While walking slowly in the park", "optb": "on a quiet summer afternoon", "optc": "a mad dog suddenly attacked him from behind", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "While he was walking slowly in the park"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Everyone visiting the house asked the young girl", "optb": "how could she kill the wolf", "optc": "single handed and without a weapon.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'how she could kill the wolf'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Many health-conscious people", "optb": "prefer  margarine", "optc": "than butter.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to butter"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The retiring principal asked his old pupils", "optb": "to take the interest in the school", "optc": "after he has retired.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "to take interest in his school"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At present juncture", "optb": "however, the supercomputer", "optc": "would be a costly toy.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "At the present juncture"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The crew were on board,", "optb": "and they soon busied themselves", "optc": "in preparing to meet the storm.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "in preparing to face the storm"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Troy was taken by Greeks", "optb": "this formed the basis of a story", "optc": "which has become famous.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Troy was taken by the Greeks"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am much pleased", "optb": "to know that", "optc": "you have topped the list.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I am very pleased"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He has not been attending", "optb": "English classes", "optc": "since one month", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "since the last one month"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is time", "optb": "we should accept all our people as equals", "optc": "and as partners in the task of building a strong and united nation.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "we should accept all our people as equal"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Twice twelve", "optb": "makes", "optc": "twenty-four", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "make"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Regretfully, profits earned by your company", "optb": "fell by 20 per cent last year", "optc": "despite higher sales.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Regrettably, profits earned by your company"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In a report issued by Indian Statistical Institute,", "optb": "the Iron and Steel Industry is investing more than any other", "optc": "Indian industry in fighting pollution.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Indian industry on fighting pollution"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is going everyday", "optb": "for a morning walk", "optc": "with his friends and neighbours", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He goes everyday"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My father goes", "optb": "to the office", "optc": "five day week.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "five days a week"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If she will be promoted", "optb": "she will get", "optc": "a higher salary.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If she is promoted"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I were him,", "optb": "I would have taught", "optc": "those cheats a lesson.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If I were he, I would have taught those cheats a lesson."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Looking back, I find that among the many impressions ofthe people of India,", "optb": "absorbed while I lived among them,", "optc": "are their reverence for great men and women.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I find that among the many impressions I got of the people of India"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If  you work hard,", "optb": "you will get good grades", "optc": "in examinations.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "C", "explanation": "in the examination"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He managed to make sense of the book", "optb": "even though it was the first time", "optc": "he read anything on the subject.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "when he read anything on the subject"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She reluctantly said that", "optb": "if nobody else was doing it", "optc": "she will do it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "she would do it"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I fail to understand", "optb": "why he replied in negative", "optc": "when the proposal was in his favour.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I failed to understand"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I have", "optb": "an appointment", "optc": "on the 9th September on five o'clock", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "on the 9th September at five o'clock"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "They", "optb": "enjoyed  thoroughly", "optc": "at the party.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "thoroughly enjoyed themselves"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The method suggested in the lecture", "optb": "enables a student to learn more quickly", "optc": "and to have remembered for a longer period of time.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "and to remember for a longer period of time"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My friend asked me", "optb": "if I can lend him my Parker pen", "optc": "for a few days.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If I could lend him my Parker pen"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The test will not need", "optb": "more than one and half hour", "optc": "to finish.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "B", "explanation": "more than one and a half hour"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The school is", "optb": "within hundred yards", "optc": "from the church.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "within a hundred yards"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "His father died of cholera", "optb": "but his mother also,", "optc": "though very weak, is out of danger.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "but his mother"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The police  broke upon the robbers", "optb": "when they were in the lonely place", "optc": "to divide their booty.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The police came upon the robbers"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since it was his first election campaign, the  candidate was confused;", "optb": "none  could clearly understand", "optc": "either the principles he stood for or the benefits he promised.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Jayesh is getting", "optb": "fatter because he", "optc": "does not take exercise at all", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "fat because he"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He loved", "optb": "none but", "optc": "his neighbour's daughter.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The criminal was", "optb": "caught, convicted the hung", "optc": "in a short period of time.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "within a short period of time"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am thinking of", "optb": "to go to Agra", "optc": "for my cousin's marriage.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "going to Agra"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In management, as you rise higher,", "optb": "the problems you face becomemore and more unstructured and you can't just fall back on", "optc": "the tools you had been", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "the problem you face become more and more unstructured and you can't afford to fall back upon"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Neeraj said", "optb": "that he would rather fail than copying", "optc": "in the examination", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he would rather fail than copy"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I had hoped to have met him yesterday", "optb": "to discuss the matter with him", "optc": "but he was not in his house, and so I could not meet him.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I had hoped to meet him yesterday"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You will come", "optb": "to my party tomorrow,", "optc": "isn't it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "won't you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I wonder", "optb": "how am I", "optc": "to do it", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "how I am going"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is not to blame", "optb": "for what has happened", "optc": "for he is in no way connected with it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He is not to be blamed"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Had you not", "optb": "reached in time", "optc": "he would have lost allour belongings.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "we would have lost all our belongings"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The man told to her", "optb": "that he had not brought his dog", "optc": "out for a walk as he was afraid that it would rain.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The man told her"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I am you", "optb": "I would have seen to it", "optc": "that I won the prize.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If I were you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is unfortunate that", "optb": "many youngsters get", "optc": "addicted to gamble.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "addicted to gambling"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Kamala's fountain-pen", "optb": "is as expensive", "optc": "as Shyama.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "as Shyama's"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When we consider all the factors, which are many,", "optb": "the number of school dropouts", "optc": "are quite disturbing.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "is quite disturbing"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She has never", "optb": "approve of him", "optc": "working as a clerk.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "approved of his"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At the station,", "optb": "I'll hire a coolie", "optc": "to carry my baggages", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to carry my baggage"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The number of marks carried by each question", "optb": "are indicated", "optc": "at the end of the question", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "is indicated"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "There is no question", "optb": "of my failing", "optc": "in the examination.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "of me failing"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She is", "optb": "no longer  popular as she has", "optc": "a friends", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "few friends"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is necessary", "optb": "that everybody", "optc": "must have a house.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "should have a house"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Students should  not take part", "optb": "in party politics and political demonstrations", "optc": "as they interfere in serious study", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'as they interfere with serious study'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "To facilitate exports and improve sales in the domestic market", "optb": "some of the improvised  fabrics and garments fabricated out  from them", "optc": "are displayed in the main pavilion.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "some of the improvised fabrics and garments made from them"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Both of you two", "optb": "can come with me", "optc": "to the play tonight", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Both of you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "No sooner did the sun rise", "optb": "when we took a hasty breakfast", "optc": "and resumed the journey.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "than we took a hasty breakfast"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The charges in this hospital", "optb": "are less than", "optc": "the hospital near my house.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "C", "explanation": "those in the hospital near my house"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The brakes and steering failed", "optb": "and  the bus ran down the hill", "optc": "without anyone being able control it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "without being controlled by anyone"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The tall three girls", "optb": "had left", "optc": "the day before.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The three tall girls"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When he was asked what is wrong with him.", "optb": "he said that he was not well.", "optc": "and asked for leave of absence for one day.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When he was asked what was wrong with him."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Wherever they go", "optb": "Indians easily adapt to", "optc": "local circumstances.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Indians easily adapt themselves to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Remember that you are part of", "optb": "the team and your success depends on the support", "optc": "you are able to give and get from your other team members.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Remember that you are a part of"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is an established fact that the transcendental American poets and philosophers.", "optb": "who lived in the latter half of the nineteenth century.", "optc": "were more influenced by Indian philosophy, in particular by Upanishadic Philosophy.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Were much influenced by Indian Philosophy in particular by Upanishadic Philosophy."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "That house", "optb": "is costing me", "optc": "ten thousand rupees", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'will cost me' or 'costs me'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Firstly you should", "optb": "think over the meaning of the words", "optc": "and then use them.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'First you should'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is true", "optb": "that God helps those", "optc": "who helps themselves.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "who help themselves"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Happily, zoos were", "optb": "unwilling to cooperate", "optc": "in a scheme that was potentially harmful to animal welfare", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "on a scheme that was potentially harmful to animal welfare"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Neither he", "optb": "nor his father is interested", "optc": "in joining the party.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "With little patience", "optb": "you will be able to", "optc": "cross this hurdle", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "with a little patience"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She was told", "optb": "to give the award to whosoever", "optc": "she thought has done the most  for the downtrodden.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "she thought had done the most for the downtrodden"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At the end of the year", "optb": "every student who had done adequate work", "optc": "was automatically promoted.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The reason why", "optb": "he was rejected", "optc": "was because he was too young.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'was that he was too young'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since we are friends", "optb": "there should be no secret", "optc": "between you and I.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "between you and me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since the attachment of airconditioned sleeping cars to all important trains,", "optb": "travelling became very pleasant,", "optc": "especially during  the summer season.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "travelling has become very pleasant"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I will have the time", "optb": "I shall try and make it", "optc": "to the zoo this afternoon.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If I have the time"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "We are four brothers and sisters living in this house", "optb": "but neither of us is", "optc": "satisfied with it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "but none of us are"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A leading textile manufacturer, one  of the fastest growing in the industry.", "optb": "is looking for a marketing manager", "optc": "to look up the marketing network of the company", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to look after the marketing network of the company"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Not one of the hundreds", "optb": "of striking workers.", "optc": "were allowed to go near the factory.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "was allowed to go near the factory"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The single biggest gainer in this process", "optb": "was ITC's Gold Flake Kings sales are estimated", "optc": "to have moved up from 50 million to 200 million sticks per month during 1987 and last year.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "was ITC's Gold Flake Kings sales of which are estimated' or 'whose sales are estimated"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "They left", "optb": "their luggages", "optc": "at the railway station.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "their luggage"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Salim and Antony are such good friends", "optb": "that one  won't go to the pictures.", "optc": "without his coming too.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "without the other's coming too"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She is", "optb": "five years", "optc": "senior than me.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "senior to me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The President had hardly spoken", "optb": "a few words", "optc": "when the microphone stopped functioning.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Locke's treatises on government toleration and education", "optb": "show a mind fully awake in", "optc": "the possibilities of social  reconstruction.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "show a mind fully alert to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You will  get", "optb": "all the information", "optc": "if you read this booklet carefully.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "you can get"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "None of the students attending your class", "optb": "answered your questions", "optc": "did  they?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'did one' or 'did any'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "An animal", "optb": "can be just as unhappy in a vast area", "optc": "or in a small one", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "as in a small one"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is working in", "optb": "a bank in New  Delhi", "optc": "for the past several months.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He has been working in"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The  scientist must follow", "optb": "his hunches and his data", "optc": "wherever it may lead.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'whenever they may lead'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Each one of the boys", "optb": "have paid", "optc": "the tuition-fee.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "has paid"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A large scale exchange of nuclear weapons", "optb": "will produce unprecedented amounts of radiation", "optc": "that can penetrate into the biological tissue.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "that can penetrate the biological tissue"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Had I", "optb": "known it earlier", "optc": "I would contact you.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I would have contacted you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He asked me", "optb": "why did I call", "optc": "him a rogue.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "why I called"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Were you", "optb": "given a choice", "optc": "or you had to do it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Had you been"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The person which was", "optb": "recommended for the position", "optc": "did not fulfil the prescribed qualifications.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The person who was"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "What does Professor Dhavan", "optb": "spend so many hours", "optc": "in the laboratory?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "why does Professor Dhavan"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The presumption that the average investor does not understand", "optb": "or take interest in the affairs of the company", "optc": "is not correct.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Shanghai is", "optb": "bigger than any city", "optc": "of the world", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "bigger than any other city"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Sheela has scored a first class", "optb": "in her final exams,", "optc": "isn't it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "hasn't she"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At the moment  the house", "optb": "was burgled the family", "optc": "attended a night  party in the neighbourhood.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The moment the house"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Scarcely had", "optb": "I arrived than", "optc": "the train left.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'I arrived when'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Though he stoutly persisted in denying his involvement in the case,", "optb": "the facts made it  very clear", "optc": "that he had hand in the cruel murder of his wife.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "that he had involved in the cruel murder of his wife."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "One of my  favourite actor", "optb": "is acting", "optc": "in this play also.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "one of my favourite actors"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Emphasis on equality of life ensures", "optb": "for the health and happiness", "optc": "of every individual.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "the health and happiness"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "There was very heavy rain last night,", "optb": "and the rivers have overflown their banks", "optc": "causing severe hardship to the people living by them.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and the rivers have overflowed their banks"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Every motorist knows", "optb": "road signs---whether symbols or colour codes--- have an immediacy", "optc": "that neither the spoken nor the written word can match.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Supposing if", "optb": "there is no bus.", "optc": "how will you get there?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "if"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Because of the emergency help", "optb": "that the patient received", "optc": "he would have died", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "But for emergency help"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He was in such hurry", "optb": "that he didn't", "optc": "wait for me", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He was in such a hurry"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Will you be", "optb": "at Board meeting", "optc": "on next Wednesday?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "next Wednesday"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Do you know", "optb": "to play", "optc": "the guitar?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "how to play"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Few scientists changed", "optb": "people's ideas as much as", "optc": "Darwin with his Theory of Evolution.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Few scientists have changed"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The course provide", "optb": "not only theoretical inputs", "optc": "but also practical training", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The course provides"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "After the humiliating exposure", "optb": "he hanged his head", "optc": "in shame.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he hung his head down"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The eminent speaker's speech", "optb": "was broadcasted over", "optc": "all the major radio-stations.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "was broadcast over"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The meeting adjourned abruptly", "optb": "by the Chairman after", "optc": "about three hours of deliberation.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The meeting was abruptly adjourned"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The company has put up an advertisement", "optb": "in newspapers", "optc": "all over the country.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The company has inserted an advertisement"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Will you lend me", "optb": "little money", "optc": "to tide over this crisis.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "a little money"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He gave them no money", "optb": "nor did help them", "optc": "in any way.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and also he did not help them"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The Sharmas", "optb": "are living in this colony", "optc": "for  the last eight  years.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "have been living in this colony"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My wife has got", "optb": "a new job", "optc": "a month ago.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "My wife got"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The ability to plan,", "optb": "organise and coordinate work is all fundamental", "optc": "to working within deadline.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to working within the deadline"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A group of friends", "optb": "want to visit", "optc": "the new plant as early as possible.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "wants to visit"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "After leaving his office", "optb": "he went directly", "optc": "to a restaurant.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He was in a hurry", "optb": "because he had an appointment", "optc": "with the company's director.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A body of volunteers", "optb": "have been organised", "optc": "to spread the message of the saint.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "has been organised"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When I get a cold", "optb": "it  takes me weeks", "optc": "to shake it off.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When I catch cold"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Another reason for pharmaceutical companies beefing up their", "optb": "OTC (Over the Country) divisions is that prescription drugs with proven safety records which have been reached", "optc": "the end of the their patent protection periodare", "optd": "allowed to be sold without a prescription. No error", "ans": "B", "explanation": "OTC divisions is that prescription drugs with proven safety records which have reached"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "There is still", "optb": "little tea", "optc": "left in the cup.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'a little tea' or 'some tea'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He says that", "optb": "his car does", "optc": "eight kilometers in a litre", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'eight kilometres per litre'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "After opening the door", "optb": "we entered into the room", "optc": "next to the kitchen", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "we entered the room"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Can I lend", "optb": "your pencil", "optc": "for a minute, please?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Can I borrow"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Last month we celebrated", "optb": "the wedding of our sister for whom", "optc": "we have been looking for a suitable alliance for three years.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "we had been looking for a suitable alliance for three years."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In an English paper", "optb": "examiners should give as much weightage to language", "optc": "as they give to contents.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am hearing", "optb": "a lot about", "optc": "the problem of AIDS these days.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I hear"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Unless you stop to make noise at once", "optb": "I will have no option but to", "optc": "bring the matter to the attention of the police.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Unless you stop making noise at once'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is generally", "optb": "more hungry", "optc": "than she is .", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since India has gained Independence", "optb": "49 years ago.", "optc": "much progress has been made in almost every field.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Since India gained independence'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He ensured his bank manager", "optb": "that he would soon", "optc": "repay the loan.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He assured his bank manager"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A free press is not a privilege", "optb": "but  the organic necessity", "optc": "in a free society.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "But an organic necessity."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He explained the matter", "optb": "at great length", "optc": "but  I was not the wiser", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "at length"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He will end up his work", "optb": "in the city", "optc": "by the end of the year.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He will end his work"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Even though the shirt is rather expensive", "optb": "but I wish to", "optc": "purchase it with my own money.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "I wish to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He enquired me", "optb": "why I had not seen him the previous day", "optc": "as I had promised to do.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "why I could not seen him the previous day"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I was there", "optb": "many  a time", "optc": "in the past.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'I have been there'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "All the four sons", "optb": "of the old man", "optc": "quarrelled between themselves.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "quarrelled among themselves"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He wanted to work all night", "optb": "but we saw that he was completely worn out", "optc": "and so we persuaded him to stop.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "but we saw that he had completely been worn out"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Mr.Smith was accused for murder", "optb": "but the court found him not guilty", "optc": "and acquitted him.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Mr.Smith was accused of murder'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She sang", "optb": "very well", "optc": "isn't it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "didn't she"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am sure that all my monthly expenses", "optb": "would exceed the income", "optc": "If I do not economic", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If I do not economise"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Whenever you go to a temple", "optb": "you must put off", "optc": "your shoes at the entrance.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "you must take off"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Having read a number of stories", "optb": "about space travel", "optc": "his dream now is about to visit the moon", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "he now dreams of visiting the moon"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The party chief made it a point to state that", "optb": "the Prime Minister and the Union Home Minister should also come.", "optc": "and they see what his party men had seen.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "and see what his party men had seen"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is easy  to see that", "optb": "a lawyer's demeanour in court", "optc": "may be prejudicial against the interests of his client.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is wiring", "optb": "for the", "optc": "last  four hours", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He has been wiring"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She walked in", "optb": "the room where the murder", "optc": "had taken place.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "She walked into"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Were he", "optb": "to see you,", "optc": "he would have been surprised.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "if he were"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I could not convince them", "optb": "because they persisted to suggest", "optc": "that I was lying.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "because they persisted in suggesting"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If  you listen with", "optb": "the question carefully", "optc": "you will be able to answer them easily", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If you listen to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is difficult", "optb": "for anyone", "optc": "to past time thus.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to pass time thus"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The customer handed over", "optb": "a hundred-rupees note", "optc": "to  the shopkeeper.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "a hundred-rupee note"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Myself and Gopal", "optb": "will take care of", "optc": "the function on sunday.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Gopal and I'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is the newspaper", "optb": "that exposes us to the widest  range", "optc": "of human experiences and behaviour.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A  small baby breathes about", "optb": "45 times per minute while", "optc": "a child of about six years breathes about 25 times per minute.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I have read", "optb": "too many books", "optc": "by R . K . Narayan.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "so many books"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He was sure", "optb": "that he should", "optc": "win the Prize.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "that he would"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is", "optb": "too intelligent", "optc": "to make a mistake.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He fell from a running train", "optb": "and would have died", "optc": "if  the villagers did not get him admitted in the nearby hospital immediately.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "if the villagers had not got him immediately admitted to a nearby hospital"}]]}